<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Answer to the case of the old East-India Company as represented by themselves to the Lords spiritual and temporal in Parliament assembled.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25581</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3395</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18101</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11936535</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11936535</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51204</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25581)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51204)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 48:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Answer to the case of the old East-India Company as represented by themselves to the Lords spiritual and temporal in Parliament assembled.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by K. Astwood, for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Columbia University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>East India Company.</term>
               <term>Foreign trade regulation --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51204:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51204:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ANSWER TO THE CASE OF THE Old <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company; As Repreſented by Themſelves TO The <hi>LORDS</hi> Spiritual <hi>and</hi> Temporal IN PARLIAMENT Aſſembled.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>K. Aſtwood,</hi> for the Author. 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:51204:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51204:2"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO THE CASE OF THE Old <hi>EAST-INDIA</hi> Company;</head>
            <p>THE Companies Caſe ſhall be anſwer'd in the Method it is ſtated by themſelves, not that they have given a true State of it with reſpect to the Act lately paſſed (for that is quite otherwiſe, as ſhall afterwards be ſhown) but to take of the Clamour which is made of invading their Property, depriving them of their Poſſeſſion and Right, ruining many Families, and the like; and therefore having to deal with Perſons, who will not anſwer what is ſaid or objected to them, only continue to make Popular Outcries they muſt be followed in their own way, till the Noiſe is
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51204:3"/>abated, and their Paſſions laid, and then it is to be hoped they will liſten to Reaſon, and conſider the Caſe as it truly ſtands, and ſhall before I finiſh be faithfully repreſented.</p>
            <p>The Company <hi>pag.</hi> 1, 2. recite ſo much, as they think for their purpoſe of the Charters granted by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> King <hi>James,</hi> King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> and King <hi>James</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> wherein is ſuggeſted, <hi>That the ſame was for the Honour of</hi> England, <hi>for the Encreaſe of Navigation, and the Advance of Trade, and the like:</hi> And I ſhall readily grant the Trade to the <hi>Eaſt-Indies</hi> to be ſuch, becauſe I really think it ſo, and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of thoſe Suggeſtions in the Charters, for it is well enough known, that thoſe who draw the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, do not think themſelves obliged to the ſtricteſt Examinations of the Suggeſtions, or to anſwer for the exact Truth of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the ſaid Charters</hi> (ſay the Company, <hi>pag.</hi> 2.) <hi>contain a Grant of the Trade to the</hi> Eaſt Indies; <hi>to the Company excluſive of all others, and by ſome of them they are conſtituted the Lords Proprietors of Bombacy, and that the perpetual Propriety of the Iſland of</hi> Sancta Helena <hi>is afterwards granted to them, and that by theſe Grants they are induced to think they have a Right in Law to the Trade, at leaſt that they ſhould have an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controverted Title to the Lands, Inheritance,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And that on this preſumption; and relying on the Publick Faith and Credit of the Great Seal of</hi> England, <hi>the Company have expended above a Million on the Credit of theſe Charters in Fortifications,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And</hi> pag. 3. <hi>That in proſpect of this Right, they have acquired Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues of</hi> 44000 l. per Annum, <hi>and many Settlements and Priviledges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Recital of theſe Charters, the Company
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51204:3"/>have omitted to give an Account of the Proviſoes inſerted therein, <hi>viz. That the reſpective Kings grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſaid Charters reſerved Power upon three Years Notice to make them void:</hi> But that being alſo a Condition in their laſt Charter, will come into Conſideration afterwards.</p>
            <p>As to the Right they pretend to the Trade ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſive of others, I do not find one Word ſaid through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their whole Caſe, to prove or maintain any ſuch Right; and this might reaſonably have been expected from them. The ſaying, <hi>They were induced to think they had a Right, and that upon that Preſumption they expended Money and purchaſed Territories,</hi> &amp;c. When at the ſame time every Lawyer muſt tell them, they had no ſuch right, and that the King by his Charter could not grant any ſuch Right excluſive of others, and that ſeveral Recoveries have been had againſt them as Law for proſecuting ſuch pretended Right: What would this be termed in other Affairs, but downright Folly and Madneſs?</p>
            <p>And as the Crown had not a Power to grant ſuch Right, ſo his preſent Majeſty hath not in Fact granted any ſuch Right excluſive, therefore the New Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribers to the Old Company, had no Inducement to think <hi>they</hi> had any ſuch Right, but if the Company <hi>(in their caſe)</hi> mean that they had a Right to the Trade, equal with all other the King's Subjects who had no Charter, that is not denied, and being granted does not ſerve their purpoſe, as will afterwards ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear.</p>
            <p>The Company go on, <hi>pag.</hi> 3. to give an Account of the Declaration of the Houſe of Commons and Houſe of Lords, <hi>That the</hi> Eaſt-India <hi>Trade ſhould be carried on in a Joint-Stock excluſive to all others,</hi> but
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51204:4"/>omit to mention their other Declaration, <hi>That it was lawful for all Perſons to Trade thither, unleſs reſtrained by Act of Parliament;</hi> and they take no Notice of the two Addreſſes, made by the Houſe of Commons, of the <hi>6th.</hi> of <hi>Feb.</hi> 1691. and 25 <hi>Feb.</hi> 1692. to diſſolve the Company.</p>
            <p>They mention Meſſage of his Majeſty to the Houſe of Commons of the <hi>14th.</hi> of <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1692. but very craftily (to ſay no worſe) omit the moſt material Part of the ſaid Meſſage, <hi>viz. That his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty required the</hi> Eaſt-India <hi>Company to anſwer directly, whether they would ſubmit to ſuch Regulations, as his Majeſty ſhould judge proper and moſt likely to advance the Trade, and the Company having fully agreed to it, and declared their Reſolution in Writing, his Majeſty commanded a Committee of his Privy Council to prepare Regulations, which they did, and offered them to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; but the Company notwithſtanding their Declaration of Submiſſion, rejected almoſt all the material Particulars, ſo that his Majeſty finding, that what poſſibly the Houſe of</hi> Commons <hi>might have expected, and indeed was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to preſerve this Trade, could not be perfected by his own Authority alone, and that the Company could not be induced to conſent to any ſuch Regulations, as might have anſwered the Intentions of the Houſe of</hi> Commons, <hi>and that the Concurrence of the Parliament is requiſite to make a Compleat and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful Settlement of this Trade, has directed all the Proceedings in this Matter to be laid before them, and recommends to them the preparing ſuch a Bill, in Oder to paſs into an Act of Parliament, as may eſtabliſh this Trade on ſuch Foundations, as are moſt likely to preſerve and advance it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Company proceed to tell <hi>How it was ſuggeſted, that their Charter was become void by their Non-payment
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51204:4"/>of the Tax impoſed upon them by Parliament, and how they the</hi> 7th. Octob. 1693. <hi>obtained a New Charter,</hi> but ſay nothing of the Eighty Odd Thouſand Pounds, paid out of the Companies Stock that ſame Year for the ſpecial Service of the Company, and great part of it for obtaining the ſaid Charter, as Sir <hi>T. C.</hi> gave an Account to the Committee of both Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Surely if the Company had a Right in Law, as they pretended <hi>they were induced to believe,</hi> there needed not ſuch Chargeable and Strenuous Solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</p>
            <p>And now we are come to the Charter it ſelf granted by his preſent Majeſty, which bears Date the <hi>7th. Octob.</hi> 1693. which was as they ſay, conteſted before the Queen and Council by thoſe they call <hi>Interlopers,</hi> upon the Hearing whereof it plainly appeared and was unanſwerably made out, that the King had not by Law, a Power to grant the Trade to ſome Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons excluſive of others, and that the then Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies Affairs were in ſuch a Condition, that it would be a plain Cheat to others, that ſhould come in upon their Stock. However Law and Reaſon failing, they had recourſe to other Means and grea Summs of Money were diſtributed (as it was acknowledged before a Committee of both Houſes of Parliament) to get a New Charter for the Old Company, and at length a New Charter was obtained, but thoſe who were concerned to adviſe his Majeſty in point of Law, were ſo juſt to their Truſt as to take care that no Right of Trade excluſive of others was granted, and alſo that the Company ſhould ſubmit to ſuch Alterations, Reſtrictions and Qualifications, as the King ſhould make before the <hi>29th. Septemb.</hi> following, and ſo on the <hi>17th. Novemb.</hi> a New
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51204:5"/>Chapter of Regulations was made, and another the <hi>28th. Septemb.</hi> 1694. Wherein (amongſt other things) was the Proviſo before mentioned, <hi>That if it ſhall appear to the King, his Heirs and Succeſſors, that the ſaid two Charters or any other Charters here<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tofore granted, ſhall not be profitable to the King, his Heirs or Succeſſors, or to this Realm, that then and from thenceforth, upon and after three Years Warning to be given to the ſaid Company, by he King, his Heirs or Succeſſors, under his or their Privy Seal or Signit Manual the ſeveral Letters Pattents,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhall ceaſe, be void, and be determined.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Security of this Charter, the Company ſay,</hi> pag. 4. <hi>they conſented to a New Subſcription, and that there was anew ſubſcribed</hi> 744000 l. <hi>and the Money brought in during the Sitting of the Parliament, and that nothing was done, ſaid or offered, againſt the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Regulations; ſo that upon the Publick Faith, (at leaſt tacitly given)</hi> 781 <hi>New Adventurers, of which many are Widows and Orphans, did ſubſcribe a large part of their Subſtance to ſupport this Trade, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a Hazardous War for the Profit and Honour of</hi> England, <hi>and that the new Adventurers thought they might without any Hazard ſubſcribe on the Security of a Charter which was ſo plainly deſigned by his Majeſty, to preſerve the</hi> Eaſt-India <hi>Traffick then in Danger of being loſt.</hi> This is the Gloſs put upon that Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action, but let us examine the Matter to the bottom, and then ſee whether it has not another Face.</p>
            <p>How this Charter was obtained appears, by the Report of the Committee of the Honourable Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> who finding great Summs of Mony paid for ſpecial Service, and obſerving that the greateſt Payment was in the Year 1693. they ſearched for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51204:5"/>the Orders for the Iſſuing of that Money, the chief of which were One dated the <hi>13th. April,</hi> 1693. at a Court of Committees in the Words following.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Governour this Day acquainting the Court with what Proceedings had been made in their Affairs towards granting a new Charter, and which what had been disburſed by him in proſecution thereof, the Court approved of the ſaid Charges, and ordered a Warrant to be made out for the ſame; and returned him thanks for his great Care, Pains and Trouble in their Service, deſiring him to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in the perfecting thereof.</hi> Another was Dated the <hi>24th.</hi> of <hi>November,</hi> 1693. at a Court of Committees held the ſame Day. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Governour this Day making a Repreſentation of what Summs of Money had been by him of lae disburſed, in the management and carrying on of the Companies, Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs for their Service, the Court approved thereof, and ordered that a Warrant be made out for making the ſame paid in Caſt accordingly, giving him their Thanks for his great Care and Pains taken therein.</hi> Another was at a Court of Committees holden the 22d. of <hi>January,</hi> 1693/4. in the Words following.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It being repreſented to the Court, that in the further Proſecution of the Companies Affairs, and in Order to their Settlement there have been ſeveral Summs of Money disburſt, amounting to</hi> 30000 l. <hi>in the whole; the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars whereof were now laid before them, on Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof had, it is Ordered, that the ſaid Monies be made paid in Caſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>The ſaid Committee of the Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> found by Examination of moſt of the Perſons pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at the aforeſaid Committees, that the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in the ſaid Committees did only in General inform them what Summs he had disburſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51204:6"/>naming the Particulars, to whom, or for what Service, which ſeveral of them ſaid was a new Courſe, ſince Sir <hi>T. C.</hi> came to be Deputy Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or Governour: but in all times before he was concerned, the Particulars of all Summs for the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Service of the Company, were declared.</p>
               <p>Further the ſaid Committee found that in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of the firſt Order, dated the <hi>13th.</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> 22275 <hi>l.</hi> was paid out of Caſh, in purſuance of that Order, and 24983 <hi>l.</hi> in purſuance of the next Order dated the <hi>24th.</hi> of <hi>November,</hi> 1693. and 30000 <hi>l.</hi> in purſuance of the laſt Order of the 22d. <hi>Jan.</hi> 1693. Amounting in all to 77258 <hi>l.</hi> beſides ſeveral ſmaller Summs amounting in the whole to 10144 <hi>l.</hi> 12 <hi>s.</hi> 3 <hi>d.</hi> Which with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Summ makes — 87402 <hi>l.</hi> 12 <hi>s.</hi> 3 <hi>d.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>And what Security was to be expected from a Charter ſo obtained, which had more in it (as it is to be feared) of Private Promiſes than Publick Faith, or ſuch a Summ of Money was ill beſtowed; and Sir <hi>B. F.</hi> on his Examination on Oath, acknowledged he had ſaid to one with whom he treated, that he would not let the Companies Money go for nothing, ſo that it is not to be wondred, that the Parliament took no Notice of the Matter whilſt the Money was paying in, when it is conſidered what is ſaid above, and Sir <hi>T. C.</hi> (amongſt other things) acquainted the Committee of both Houſes, <hi>That there were ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Contracts, ſome to the Value of</hi> 60000 l. <hi>on Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of procuring a new Charter, and others to ther Value of</hi> 40000 l. <hi>on Account of procuring an Act of Parliament:</hi> By ſuch means it might be huſh'd for a while, but it was not long before the Parliament took Publick Notice of it, and if the greater Affairs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51204:6"/>of the Nation had not been ſo urgent, and the Seſſions been ſo near an End, perhaps the Company might have had Juſtice done them then, and been paſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of any Imaginary Injuſtice done them now.</p>
            <p>It appears therefore very plainly, that it was not for the Profit and Honour of the Nation, and to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the Trade, that the New Subſcribers came in, but they were deluded into it by a Charter obtained by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct Means, and by the hopes of an Act of Parliament to confirm it, to be obtained in the ſame Manner.</p>
            <p>The Trade would have been much better preſerved, and more to the Honour of the Nation, if no ſuch underhand Practices had been carried on; and if ſome Perſons thinking themſelves to have a greater reach than others, or being deceived by the Old Companies mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Majeſty believe their Stock to be worth 750000 <hi>l.</hi> and by afterwards ſharing 325000 <hi>l.</hi> of the New Subſcribers Money amongſt themſelves, or by the Perſons failing them who had promiſed to get an Act of Parliament, or by Loſſes at Sea, or by what other Means ſoever it were, happened to fail in their Expectation, who are anſwerable for it but themſelves? If any Widows were drawn in, it was but few, and that not for much, to be ſure; but that's a ſtate Cry, and they and all others had Warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enough by the Tranſactions before the Council, and by publick Prints, in one of which Entituled, <hi>Reaſons propoſed for the Encouragement of all People to underwrite to the New Subſcriptions, appointed to be made to the late</hi> Eaſt-India <hi>Companies Stock;</hi> after an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their Affairs, this Caution was given <hi>pag.</hi> 7. <hi>If People will put out their Eyes, and always be thus bubbled out of their Money, as well as their Senſes, they may go on till they are weary, and perhaps this is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51204:7"/>done, that the old pretence might ſtill be urged for their Continuance,</hi> viz. <hi>That a great many Widows, Orphans, and Innocent, and Ignorant People might not be cheated and undone, if they ſhould be diſſolved, but let not the ſaid Gentlemen deceive themſelves and others, doubtleſs the Parliament will not be thus affronted, but will take notice of theſe Proceedings, and aſſert the Right and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the Subject to the Freedom of this Trade,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>If Perſons will then adventure their Money after all this, they muſt take their Fate, and I think if ſuch a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedure eſcapes cenſure it is a happy Iſſue, though they come to ſome Loſs. (not to ſay any thing of the Violences and Irregularities of the Old Company.) For,</p>
            <p>10 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. One <hi>John Peach</hi> was arraigned at the Parliament Bar, for that he had obtained of the King a Monopoly for Sweet Wines. The Pattent after great Advice and Diſpute adjudged void, and before his Face in open Parliament cancelled, becauſe he had exacted 3 <hi>s.</hi> 4 <hi>d.</hi> for every Tun of Wine, himſelf adjudged to Priſon, until he had made Reſtitution of all that ever he had received, and not delivered till after a Fine of 500 <hi>l.</hi> paid to the King, which at that time was a great Summ of Money.</p>
            <p>In Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s time upon Complaint in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of Pattents granted for Monopolies, moſt of them were immediately revoked, and the reſt left to the Law.</p>
            <p>In King <hi>James</hi> the <hi>1ſt.</hi> time, an Act of Parliament paſſed, to make void a Charter for the ſole Trade to <hi>Spain,</hi> and another againſt all Monopolies, and though the Pattents for ſome Trades with joint-ſtocks, (whilſt the Trades for which they were granted were in their Infancy) have been permitted for the ſettling
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51204:7"/>of a Trade, and till the firſt Adventurers have reaped ſome reaſonable compenſation for their firſt Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking and Adventures, yet afterwards when thoſe Trades have encreaſed and become great, the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Nation has always thought fit, to open a Way for the Kingdom to receive a General Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit thereby.</p>
            <p>This as to Pattents in General, and from the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident in <hi>Ed.</hi> the <hi>3d.</hi> Time, I ſhall make no Inference, but leave it to the Company themſelves, only I ſhall obſerve, it was never eſteemed a Breach of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith, and Credit of the Great Seal or a Dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation from the Honour of our Kings, to have their Pattents annull'd by Parliament; when the Grants were thought by that Grand Council of the Nation not to be profitable, or to be againſt the Common Right of the Subject, whatever the expreſs Covenants in thoſe Grants were, and no King or Queen by any Grant or Pattent, thought thhemſelves bound in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or Conſcience not to paſs an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to make void ſuch Pattent, and the reaſon is plain; the King being buſied in the many arduous Affairs of the Kingdom, cannot be ſuppoſed to know always what he may legally grant, and is oftentimes deceived in his Grants, and for that reaſon they are often annulled by the ordinary courſe of Law, and ſo might this Companies Pattent have been without any Wrong or Injuſtice to the Company, for all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons having a Right by Law to trade to the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> unleſs excluded by Parliament; the King by his Charter could not grant to the Company any new Right to the Trade, only the Priviledges of an Incorporated Body, but the Parliament juſtly bearing a high Veneration to his preſent Majeſty, who has
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51204:8"/>run ſo great Hazard, and performed ſo Great and Glorious Atchievements for the Honour and Weal of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, have notwithſtanding taken care in the late Act paſſed, that nothing ſhould interfere with his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Pattent, before which Time the Caſe ſtood thus.</p>
            <p>The Company had a Pattent of Incorporation from his preſent Majeſty, with Power to trade to the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> and other Priviledges, without any expreſs Clauſe to exclude others, or any Covenant (as was in the former Charters from the Crown) that his Majeſty would not grant Licenſe to others, to trade thither during the continuance of the ſaid Charter, but with the expreſs Proviſo before-mentioned, to have power to make void the ſaid Charters upon three years notice, if it ſhall appear to the King, that the ſaid Charters ſhall not be profitable to the King or this Realm.</p>
            <p>During the continuance of theſe laſt Charters, therefore even according to the Charters themſelves; all other the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> had a Right to Trade to the <hi>Eaſt-Indies</hi> as well as the Company, and many uſed that Right and actually traded thither without Interruption, not only as by Law, but even as by thoſe Charters they might; and no doubt, but the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo trading would have been contented, if the Trade might have been continued to be carried on, as it was before this laſt Seſſion of Parliament; they ſought no Alteration, the Law as it ſtood was their Protection and Security; and the Charters the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany had, and the Money their Joint-ſtock was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to ſcatter up and down, was the Companies Security; and the private Traders thought theirs as good as the Companies.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:51204:8"/>
            <p>But though the Company in their Caſe, talk ſo much of their Dependance on the Security of their Charters, and the Right in Law which they had by them, yet they themſelves were convinced that their Right was not well founded, and therefore as they had ſought formerly to get an Act of Parliament, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which they knew well enough, they had no ſuch Legal Right as they pretended; ſo this Seſſions they were for making another Attempt, and in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ſucceed they firſt made an Offer to lend 700000 <hi>l.</hi> to the Government, to have the Trade to themſelves excluſive of all others. The other Subjects of <hi>England</hi> being about to be excluded by ſuch means from the Trade, were ſoon alarm'd, and that not without Reaſon, and begin to think with themſelves how to preſerve their Right in the Trade, and their honeſt Reſult was, That if the Parliament thought fit to raiſe Money by that Trade, they deſired only to fare as the reſt of their Fellow Subjects, and they would be ready to lend to the Government as well as the Company, and a much larger Summ.</p>
            <p>Hereupon the Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> thought fit to raiſe a Fund of 8 <hi>l. per Cent.</hi> for the Payment of the Intereſt of Two Millions, and that ſuch as lent their Money ſhould be intituled to Trade (for ſo much as they lent) to the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> which was no more than this. In the preſent Exegency of Affairs, the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> rather than any other Trade, only they judged it reaſonable to give all an equal Liberty to come in, whereas the Company would have had it par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial, and that <hi>they</hi> only, and ſuch as would have been again drawn in by them, and come in upon their bottom, ſhould have had the Benefit. This was the true Caſe.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:51204:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 6. The Company ſay, <hi>That after the Bill was brought in,</hi> viz. <hi>the</hi> 10th. <hi>of</hi> June, <hi>They did agree to ſubmit their preſent Stock to a Valuation of</hi> 50 l. <hi>per</hi> Cent. <hi>viz.</hi> 20 l. <hi>per</hi> Cent. <hi>for their dead Stock, and</hi> 30 l. <hi>per</hi> Cent. <hi>for their quick Stock, which they were contented to warrant at the ſaid Summs, and upon theſe Terms they offered to open their Books for new Subſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in Order to raiſe the two Millions, and afterwards to aſcertain the Payments of the ſaid two Millions, they had a General Court on the</hi> 20th. <hi>of</hi> June (<hi>which was when the Bill was well nigh</hi> paſſed the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous) <hi>in which they agreed to an immediate Subſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by private Adventurers,</hi> 20000 l. <hi>to be paid as the firſt Payment ſubject to make good the ſubſequent Payments, which Subſcription was accordingly made.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the Propoſal as the Company expreſt it in their own Caſe, and from whence it is talkt up and down the Town, as if the Company made an Offer of Two Millions, and that it is Hardſhip upon them, that they who were in Poſſeſſion and offer'd the ſame Summs, ſhould not be accepted rather than others; and the Company inſinuate this when they ſay, <hi>Pag.</hi> 5. <hi>That formerly it has been the conſtant Cuſtom in Farms, Bargains and Offers of the like Nature, not to cloſe with a new Propoſal till the firſt Bidder be asked, whether he is able to advance further, and that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their Charter, and the Right they have to the Trade, they were early told their Propoſal ſhould be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, though they offered the two Millions in queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I think with Submiſſion, if any preference had been ſhewn by a Parliament, it would have been to thoſe who were willing to ſtand by, and adhere to the Legal Rights of the Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> and not to thoſe who ſtrive by undue Means to gain
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51204:9"/>and ſupport Grants not founded on Law, however the Parliament have thought fit to make no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and therein the private Traders acquieſce.</p>
            <p>But as to the Companies offering to raiſe two Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, when what they and others call an Offer, is taken to pieces and examined it will be found only an Evaſion, and no ſuch Offer in reality with an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention that it ſhould take effect, only an amuſement to gain time, and ſo to baffle the Bill. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. They agreed to ſubmit their Stock to a Valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of 50 <hi>l.</hi> per <hi>Cent. viz.</hi> their dead ſtock 20 <hi>l.</hi> per <hi>Cent.</hi> and their quick Stock 30 <hi>l.</hi> per <hi>Cent.</hi> which they were contented to warrant at the ſaid Summs, and upon theſe Terms they offered to open their Books for New Subſcriptions, in Order to raiſe the two Millions.</p>
            <p>They knew very well, that others did not value their Stock at any thing near ſo much, and that no Body would be gulled a ſecond time to come into <hi>them,</hi> and not only to take their Stock at 50 <hi>l.</hi> per <hi>Cent.</hi> which was believed not to be worth 20 <hi>l.</hi> but to join with <hi>them,</hi> and become ſubject to all their intricate Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts and Incumbrances, and anſwerable for all their Misdemeanours which the Stock if there be any muſt anſwer for, if the Parliament ſhould think fit to call them to an Account, which poſſibly may come to paſs, if the Company continue to provoke them by cenſuring and aſperſing their Proceedings, becauſe it has not ſuited their extravagant Expectations.</p>
            <p>Well, this they were aware of, and therefore to mend the Matter, they were contented to warrant their quick ſtock at 30 <hi>l.</hi> per <hi>Cent. They were content,</hi> that is, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany were content that the Stock which moſt People be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve is not worth 3 <hi>l.</hi> per <hi>Cent.</hi> ſhould warrant it ſelf to be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51204:10"/>worth 30 <hi>l.</hi> per <hi>Cent.</hi> and upon whom ſhould any one have come for making good this Warrant and when? This is plainly to offer nothing at all. But,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly.</hi> To aſcertain the Payment of the two Millions, they ſubſcribed 200000 <hi>l.</hi> ſubject to make good the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent Payments, let us conſider this a little.</p>
            <p>Upon the Parliaments Acceptance of this their Propoſal, they might reaſonably expect in Act to be paſſed in their Favour, and then if no more then the ſaid 200000 <hi>l.</hi> had been ſubſcribed, (as for the Reaſons before-mentioned, it is more than probable there would not) what would have been the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence? Why,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> The Company would have obtained what they have been ſo long aiming at, an Act of Parliament excluſive, for the Summ of 200000 <hi>l.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly.</hi> The King would have been defeated of a much more conſiderable Loan, the Company offering Subſcriptions for 200000 <hi>l.</hi> and others delivered in Subſcriptions for above 1200000 <hi>l.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as the Companies Caſe ſays, <hi>pag.</hi> 9. <hi>All things are ſeen where every one are concerned to look,</hi> ſo the Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> (wherein are ſo many piercing Eyes, and all concerned to look) ſoon ſaw, that this Propoſal was in no ſort adapted to anſwer the End, that is, the Parliaments End, to get the King Two Millions of Money; though it would fully have anſwered the Companies End (if it had been complied with) to have got the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade ſettled on them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſive of others for the Summ of 200000 <hi>l.</hi> which would have been to them a very good Bargain, for they knew their Stock would preſently have advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced twice that Summ.</p>
            <p>Well now, we are (going along with the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51204:10"/>Caſe) at length come to the Bill, <hi>Which</hi> they ſay, <hi>pag.</hi> 6. <hi>highly tends to the prejudice of the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies Charters and Rights thereby granted, and alſo to deprive them of their Property which they have in Lands of Inheritance, and other Eſtates and Intereſts in For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Parts to the Value of</hi> 44000 l. <hi>per</hi> Annum, <hi>which Bill likewiſe by undeniable conſequence deprives them of their Poſſeſſion and Right in ſeveral Forts and Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications, the Purchaſe and Improvement of which, have at ſeveral times coſt them above a Million of Pounds Sterling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If a Perſon is Tenant at Will, or has a Leaſe for Years of ceretain Ground; and woll build, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe lay out Money extravagantly upon what he knows he may be turned out of, at the Pleaſure of the Lord of whom he holds, or at moſt upon three Years Warning; is there any Injuſtice in his Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord to make Uſe of the Power reſerved upon the Demiſe, or is any one to be blamed but the Tenants own Indiſcretion; the Company knew upon what Terms they had their Charters, that all of them in the former Reigns had no Foundation in Law for granting the Trade excluſive, nay, the moſt of them contained a power of Revocation on three Years No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice: And therefore in what they ſay they have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended, they ſhould have had a regard to the Terms on which they held thoſe Grants. However, their Clamour herein is otherwiſe without Ground, for if they have ſince their beginning as they ſay expended a Million, they have got it over and over by the Trade and divided it out, and the Revenues they pretend to in <hi>India</hi> coſts them much more than the Income.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:51204:11"/>
            <p>I agree with the Companies Caſe, <hi>pag.</hi> 6. That this Actis directly contrary to all their former Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in that point, where the Trade is granted to them excluſive of all others, and with great Reaſon. It is the Buſineſs, and ought always to be the Care of Parliaments, to preſerve the Rights of all the King's Subjects equally; and never was a more equal, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and juſt Act paſſed, as will appear by and by.</p>
            <p>But tho' the Act is contrary to the Charters of former Reigns in that point, it is in nothing contrary to the Charter of his preſent Majeſty; as before has been ſaid.</p>
            <p>The Company ſay, <hi>pag.</hi> 6. That no Breach or For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture of their Charters is charged upon them, if ſo, it is not becauſe by Law it could not be done, for they have done enough to forfeit 100 Charters, and to ſubject them to grievous Fines beſides, if Advantages were taken either by the King or Parliament: But without that, the Proviſo gives the King a full power to determine them in three Years, <hi>&amp;c fruſtra fit per plura quod fieri poteſt per pauciora.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Proviſo is as hath been ſaid to this Effect, that if it ſhall appear to his Majeſty, that the ſaid two Charters ſhall not be profitable to the King or to this Realm, that then upon three Years Notice or Warning, the ſame ſhall ceaſe and be void.</p>
            <p>How could the Reſervation have been more full than this, It is not, if the Trade ſhall appear unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, nay, norif the Company ſhall appear unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, but if the two Charters granted by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, or any other of the former Charters ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to his Majeſty, not to be profitable to him or to the Realm. Then <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:51204:11"/>
            <p>And how can the unprofitableneſs of any of the ſaid Charters appear more plainly and effectually to his Majeſty, then by the Judgment of both Houſes of Parliament.</p>
            <p>And now I ſhall in ſhort ſtate the Caſe truly as it is.</p>
            <p>Before the laſt Seſſions of Parliament the Company had a Right to Trade to the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> and ſo had all other the King's Subjects, and all went on trading thither as they ſaw fit, all were alike ſubject to the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of the War, and all had born their ſhare of Loſſes, and all hoped with the Peace and Time to repair them.</p>
            <p>The Company not contented with the Right they ſay they had, (though the Law was open and they as well as others, might have had Redreſs in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall</hi> for the Invaſion of any Right) They ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to the Parliament to get others excluded from their Right, and the others then apply to preſerve their Right, and the Company being the Aggreſſors, think to come off (according to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proverb and Practice of many) by crying <hi>Whore</hi> firſt; for they have thereby brought a Tax upon the whole Trade, and if any have reaſon to complain, it is the private Traders, who before had a Right and could have traded as they pleaſed; but now are obliged to trade for no more than they lend the Government.</p>
            <p>The Parliament duly weighing this great Affair, came to Reſolutions Equal and Honourable at ſuch a Juncture, obliging all to lend to the Government ſo much as they deſire to be concerned in the Trade.</p>
            <p>In their Caſe <hi>pag.</hi> 9. they find fault, that the Bill allows Forreigners as well as the King's Subjects to ſubſcribe to the Two Millions, whereby they will be let into the Secrets and Myſteries of it; which as the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51204:12"/>Company are ready to ſhew, may produce Effects very pernicious and dangerous to the General Intereſt of the Nation. Whereas in the Companies Anſwer to the Regulations propoſed by his Majeſty, dated 20 <hi>May,</hi> 1692. in Anſwer to the <hi>8th.</hi> Propoſition about Subſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers aking Oath it is his own Money, amongſt other things they ſay, Thirdly, <hi>If ſuch a Limitation be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſable, certainly ſome Nation or other would have hit upon the Expedient before this time, whereas on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary the wiſe</hi> Dutch <hi>indulge and favour the very</hi> Jews, <hi>and the more for buying the greater Stock, of whom one Man by Name</hi> Swaſſo, <hi>had at one time about</hi> 75000 l. <hi>Stock, the</hi> French <hi>King likewiſe for the Encouragement of large Subſcriptions in that Stock, propounded many conſiderable Priviledges and Immunities both to Natives and Forreigners, proportionable to the greatneſs of their Subſcriptions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Company will argue for and agaiſt the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance of Forreigners as it ſerves their turns, and ſo their Diſcourſe about the Town is to the ſame Effect, one while they ſay their Factors will cheat them of all they have there; and another while, that they would ſend out all that ever they can into their Hands and truſt them further. Upon the whole it is Evident.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Company and all other his Majeſties Subjects, had before this Act an equal Right to the Trade to the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> unleſs excluded or reſtrained by Act of Parliament.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That there has no hardſhip been put upon the Old of New Subſcribers in the Old Company, nor any Right of theirs invaded, but rather a great Favour is done them, in not puniſhing them for their Illegal Practices.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:51204:12"/>
            <p n="3">3. That the old Company made no Propoſal to lend the Two Millions, but ſuch as muſt have proved ineffectual to the Neceſſity of the Government, and deſtructive of the Rights of the Subject.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the Company heretofore thought it an Advantage to admit Forreigners into the Company, and many are actually now in the preſent Company, though now in their Caſe they argue againſt it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
